Finding Aid for Paul Blanshard Papers, 1912-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Writings and related materials circa 1917-1978
  - Articles and Speeches
    - 1917
      [4-41]
      - "The Immoral Reflections of a Preacher" (Box 4)
    - 1921
      [4-42]
      - "The Class Struggle in a Ball-Room" May 4, 1921 (Box 4)
      - "Turning the Tables on the Newspapers" August 16, 1921 (Box 4)
    - 1923
      [4-43]
      - "Company Unions or National Unions?-A Debate" July 25, 1923 (Box 4)
      - "Mussolini Starts a War" September 26, 1923 (Box 4)
    - 1924-1927
      [4-44]
      - "Liberalism in the Colleges" September 17, 1924 (Box 4)
      - "Military 'Glory' in the Colleges" February 18, 1925 (Box 4)
      - "The Inquiring Reporter in Shanghai" September 16, 1925 (Box 4)
      - "Hankow Swings to the Right" August 31, 1927 (Box 4)
      - "The Future of the Chinese Revolution" September 7, 1927 (Box 4)
      - "Women of the New China Loose Their Age-Old Shackles" November 6, 1927 (Box 4)
    - Syndicated newspaper columns
      - January 1927 (Box 4)
        [4-45]
      - February 1927 (Box 4)
        [4-46]
      - March and undated 1927 (Box 4)
        [4-47]
    - May-July 1928
      [4-48]
      - "New Bedford Goes on Strike" May 23, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "The Southern Cotton Mills Reply" June 6, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "The Future of China" July 1928 (Box 4)
    - August 1928
      [4-49]
      - "The Defeat of the Coal Strike" August 1, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on economy; imperialism; and social insurance August 8, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "The Southern Bishops"; Comments on labor strikes August 15, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on progress August 22, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "The Crisis in Manchuria" August 29, 1928 (Box 4)
    - September-December, 1928
      [4-50]
      - Comments on Courts and Strikes; Debs Radio Station September 5, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "What Brookwood Means" September 12, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "Labor Strategy" September 19, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "College Morality" October 10, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on New Bedford strike October 17, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "Hoover and the Scripps-Howard Press" October 24, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Norman Thomas and 1928 election; atheism; "Britain Talks Politics", October 31, 1928 (Box 4)
      - "Profiteering on Grief" October, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on centralized railroad system; labor strikes; "Unregenerate Diplomacy" November 7, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Armistice Day; Japan; Southern education November 14, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on unemployment payments; college football; fundamentalism December 5, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Norman Thomas' presidential campaign; labor movement in Germany; athletic deaths; "A Swan Song for Lame Ducks" December 12, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on the Department of the Interior and I.W.W.; "Undemocratic Democracy"; "It Costs Money to Die" December 19, 1928 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Federal Radio Commission; Boulder Dam; the future of small independent newspapers; "Stop the Cruiser Bill" December 26, 1928 (Box 4)
    - January-April, 1929
      [4-51]
      - Comments on Federal Council of Churches; Amalgamated Clothing Workers; Corporate finance January 2, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on China; "Exit Sin" January 9, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Manchuria; the "Power Trust"; Governor Franklin D. Roosevelt; "Ask Mr. Mellon" January 23, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on American political corruption; anti-strike actions; public ownership in California; "Old and Poor"; "Salvation Limited" January 30, 1929 (Box 4)
      - "Wanted-A Consumers' Advocate" February 6, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Protestantism; "See the Job Through, Mr. Rockefeller!" February 13, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Federal Reserve Board; suburban parks; "Salt Creek The Biggest Oil Scandal" February 20, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Tom Mooney case; U.S. Latin American Policy; China; American Penal system; "The Churches and Marriage" March 6, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Standard Oil; compulsory military training in college March 20, 1929 (Box 4)
      - "From Peruna to Piffle"; "Labor's Predicament" March 27, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on political corruption; business contacts with Russia; Labor Party in England; "Shifting Immigration" April 3, 1929 (Box 4)
      - "Pat and the D.A.R." April 10, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on oil production; Southern attitude toward labor organization; China; "Crazy Economics" April 17, 1929 (Box 4)
      - "Communism in Southern Cotton Mills" April 24, 1929 (Box 4)
    - May-June 1929
      [4-52]
      - Comments on tariffs; Southern textile workers May 1, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on political corruption; union attitudes in South and Pennsylvania; Tom Mooney case; "One Hundred Per Cent Americans on Strike" May 8, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on birth control controversy; Latin America; "How to Live on Forty-six Cents a Day" May 15, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on unionization in South May 22, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on unionization in South; "Russia Looks Ahead" June 5, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on reapportionment of U.S. Congress; "Fifty-six to One" June 12, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Unionization in South; Japan; "The Labor Cabinet" June 19, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on oil industry; Mrs. Hoover and Mrs. Oscar DePriest June 26, 1929 (Box 4)
    - July-October, 1929
      [4-53]
      - Comments on J.P. Morgan; Textile manufacturing July 3, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on oil scandals; China; "Say It With Deposits"; "Uncle Sam's Electric Empire" July 10, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on unionization in South; Tom Mooney case; "Can We Abolish Sunday?" July 17, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on international tennis; wearing pajamas in public August 7, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on freedom of speech in Philadelphia; British recognition of Russia; "Justice in Gastonia" August 14, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Russo-Chinese confrontation; Southern labor movement; "Baby Motor Cars"; "Enter Cupid" August 21, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on China August 28, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on "power trust"; Southern Unionization; "Morals and Movies" September 18, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on Southern unionization; British recognition of Russia; Japan; "Insurance by the Bucket" October 9, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on labor movement in South; China October 16, 1929 (Box 4)
      - Comments on movies in education; China; "Labor Asleep" October 23, 1929 (Box 4)
    - 1930-1934
      [4-54]
      - "Let's Build a World without Unemployment" December 1930 (Box 4)
      - "Dollars to Disarmament" Autumn 1931 (Box 4)
      - "What Seabury Has Revealed" January 1932 (Box 4)
      - "Wanted A New Federal Constitution" January 25, 1932 (Box 4)
      - "Tammany, The Roosevelt Myth"; "What a Socialist America Would Like" (in A Plan for Action: Official, 1932 Campaign Handbook of the Socialist Party), 1932 (Box 4)
      - "The Roosevelt Leadership" October 31, 1933 (Box 4)
      - Confidential statement concerning resignation from Socialist Party 1933 (Box 4)
      - "Reviving Local Government" March 6, 1934 (Box 4)
      - Untitled speech on federal government power 1934 (Box 4)
    - 1936-1939
      [4-55]
      - "Shall We Scrap the Constitution--A Debate" 1936 (Box 4)
      - High school commencement address January 30, 1936 (Box 4)
      - "The Future of the Professions in America" 1937 (Box 4)
      - "Reform or Bust" October 28, 1939 (Box 4)
    - 1940-1941
      [4-56]
      - "Labor and National Defense" May 22, 1940 (Box 4)
      - Untitled speech on American aid to England September 25, 1940 (Box 4)
      - Keynote-address to American Labor Party September 28, 1940 (Box 4)
      - "A Battle Lost, A War to Win" December, 1940 (Box 4)
      - "Resolved That the Power of the Federal Government Should be Increased" January 1, 1941 (Box 4)
      - Debate on county reform May 5, 1941 (Box 4)
    - 1942-1946
      [4-57]
      - "Youth, Crime and War" May 17, 1942 (Box 4)
      - "Negro Delinquency in New York" October, 1942 (Box 4)
      - "America's Plan for the Colonial World" February, 1945 (Box 4)
      - "Colonies and World Peace" January, 1946 (Box 4)
      - "Puerto Rico Moves a Step Ahead" August 4, 1946 (Box 4)
    - 1947
      [4-58]
      - "Independence No Solution" April 5, 1947 (Box 4)
      - "Jim Crow at the Canal" May 1947 (Box 4)
      - "The Roman Catholic Church in Medicine" November 1, 1947 (Box 4)
      - "The Sexual Code of the Roman Catholic Church" November 8, 1947 (Box 4)
      - "The Catholic Church and Education" November 15, 1947 (Box 4)
    - 1948
      [4-59]
      - "The Catholic Church and Fascism" April 17, 1948 (Box 4)
      - "Roman Catholic Censorship Books and Magazines" May 1, 1948 (Box 4)
      - Roman Catholic Censorship Movies" May 8, 1948 (Box 4)
      - "The Catholic Church and American Democracy Wit" May 29, 1948 (Box 4)
      - "The Catholic Church and American Democracy" June 5, 1948 (Box 4)
      - "Let Catholic Liberals Reply" August, 1948 (Box 4)
      - "New York Public Schools Ban on The Nation Protested" December, 1948 (Box 4)
    - January- May 4, 1949 (Box 5)
      [5-1]
      - "Twilight of Caribbean Imperialism" January 22, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "The Catholic Church and Honest Advertising" April 13, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "The Catholic Church and Marriage" April 20, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "The Catholic Church and Annulment" April 27, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "The Catholic Price for Cooperation" May 4, 1949 (Box 5)
    - May 21-September 1949
      [5-2]
      - "Billions for Brass How the Pentagon Squanders Your Money" May 21, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "Pork Barrels in the Pentagon" June 4, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "Glossary of Double-Talk" June 11, 1949 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding power of Catholic Church June 11, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "Popular Fallacies about the Roman Catholic Church" September, 1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950
      [5-3]
      - "The Catholic Church and Politics" February 10, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "Second Round for Israel?" April 15, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "Israel-Church and State" May 27, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican and Israel" July 1, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "Can We do Business with the Vatican" July 29, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "The Holy Year Fact and Fiction" September 23, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "Protestants in Italy" November 11, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "Population and Poverty: The Birth Control Struggle in Italy" November 25, 1950 (Box 5)
      - "The Catholic Church and Politics" 1950, 3 copies (Box 5)
    - 1951
      [5-4]
      - "The Vatican Versus the Public Schools: Italy" January 20, 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican Versus the Public Schools: The Netherlands" January 27, 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican Versus the Public Schools: France" March 3, 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican Versus the Public Schools: Belgium" March 24, 1951 (Box 5)
      - "Population and Poverty in Italy" September, 1951 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding Vatican ambassador November 3, 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican Versus the Public Schools: The Challenge to America and Europe" 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican and Religious Discrimination" 1951 (Box 5)
      - "The Catholic Problem" (regarding controversy over American Freedom and Catholic Power) 1951 (Box 5)
    - 1952-1953
      [5-5]
      - "One-sided Diplomacy: The Ambassador to the Vatican" January, 1952 (Box 5)
      - "The Challenge of a Vatican:Ambassador" January 3, 1952 (Box 5)
      - "Birth Control and Catholic Power in America" July, 1952 (Box 5)
      - "The Case of Archbishop O'Hara" (Papal Nuncio to Ireland) May 6, 1953 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding the Vatican June 10, 1953 (Box 5)
      - "The State and Catholic Power in the United States" December 9, 1953 (Box 5)
      - "The Bishops' Pronouncement" 1953 (Box 5)
    - 1954-1956
      [5-6]
      - Letter to editor regarding a Catholic critic January, 1954 (Box 5)
      - "Anti-Intellectualism in Communications" January, 1955 (Box 5)
      - "Malice in Blunderland: A Report on the Foundations" January 15, 1955 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding city employees October 14, 1955 (Box 5)
      - "The Sectarian Battlefront" 1955 (Box 5)
      - "Without Fear or Favor" 1955 (Box 5)
      - "An Imaginary Cross-Examination of Cardinal Spellman" January 25, 1956 (Box 5)
      - "The Sectarian Assault Upon the Constitution" January 26, 1956 (Box 5)
      - "The Separation of Church and State: The American Way" February 28, 1956 (Box 5)
      - Statement before Treasury Department concerning taxes and private schools April 10, 1956 (Box 5)
      - "Must We Tolerate Intolerance" July, 1956 (Box 5)
      - "American Freedom and Catholic Power" December 8, 1956 (Box 5)
      - "Official Statements from Catholic Sources Regarding Education" 1956 (Box 5)
    - 1957-1958
      [5-7]
      - "Communism and the Catholic Mind" January, 1957 (Box 5)
      - "The Challenge of Clerical Power" March 8, 1957 (Box 5)
      - "American Freedom and Catholic Power" May 1957 (Box 5)
      - "Public Money and Schools" August, 1957 (Box 5)
      - "Has Catholic Power Changed?" 1957 (Box 5)
      - "Protestant Freedom and Communist Power" February, 1958 (Box 5)
      - "In Defense of Separation: A Guide to Action" May 1958 (Box 5)
      - "Challenge Legality of Cardinals' Vote for Pope" October 15, 1958 (Box 5)
      - "The Papal Election and American Law" November 19, 1958 (Box 5)
      - "The Papal Election" November 19, 1958 (Box 5)
      - Comments on Papal election December, 1958 (Box 5)
      - "Birth Control and Freedom of Choice" December, 1958 (Box 5)
    - 1959
      [5-8]
      - "Our Right to Heresy" February, 1959 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding John F. Kennedy March 27, 1959 (Box 5)
      - "Ecclesiastical Justice in Spain I: The 'Crime' of Antonio Mendez" September 23, 1959 (Box 5)
      - "Ecclesiastical Justice in Spain II: The 'Crime' of Pastor Nunez" September 30, 1959 (Box 5)
      - "The Papal Election and American Law" October, 1959 (Box 5)
      - "The Liberal Approach to Church and State" 1959 (Box 5)
      - "The Bus Wedge" 1959 (Box 5)
      - "The Tuition Wedge" 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960
      [5-9]
      - "A Protestant View of a Catholic President" May 10, 1960 (Box 5)
      - "Challenge of Catholic Power" June 2, 1960 (Box 5)
      - "Separation of Church and State" October 10, 1960 (Box 5)
      - "Religion in Politics" panel discussion November 10, 1960 (Box 5)
      - "The Battle Continues: Religion in the Public Schools" December, 1960 (Box 5)
      - "A Catholic in the White House" panel discussion 1960 (Box 5)
      - Protestant-Catholic Tensions (a dialogue) 1960, 2 copies (Box 5)
    - 1961
      [5-10]
      - "Church-State Separation and the Future of Catholic Power" January 5, 1961 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding tax exempt status of Christian Brothers February 10, 1961 (Box 5)
      - Statement before U.S. House of Representatives Subcommittee on education March 16, 1961 (Box 5)
      - "The State and the Rights of Individual Conscience" September, 1961 (Box 5)
      - "Religion, Aid to Education and the Future" October, 1961 (Box 5)
      - "The Battle Continues" 1961 (Box 5)
        (postlude to One Woman's Flight by Vashti Cromwell McCollum)
      - Statement before Senate Judiciary Committee concerning prayer in public schools 1961 (Box 5)
      - Statement on federal aid to education 1961 (Box 5)
      - Statement concerning Congressional support for aid to Sectarian Schools 1961 (Box 5)
      - "The Future of Catholic Power" 1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962-1963
      [5-11]
      - "Christian Brothers surrender $4,000,000 in Liquor Profits to Uncle Sam" February, 1962 (Box 5)
      - "Is Federal Aid to Parochial Schools Constitutional?" February 14, 1962 (Box 5)
      - "Catholic Versus Protestant in Portuguese Africa" Winter 1962 (Box 5)
      - "The American Answer to Catholic Power" 1962 (Box 5)
      - "The Supreme Court Prayer Decision" 1962 (Box 5)
      - "The Church and the State" January, 1963 (Box 5)
      - Statement before Senate Subcommittee on Armed Services concerning conscientious objection and selective service draft March 12, 1963 (Box 5)
      - "The Big Decision" July, 1963 (Box 5)
        (Supreme Court's decision on Bible reading in public schools)
    - 1964-1966
      [5-12]
      - Comments on Vatican II March, 1964 (Box 5)
      - Eulogy on Elinore Morehouse Herrick November 15, 1964 (Box 5)
      - "Religious Liberty Limited: A Report from Vatican II" February, 1966 (Box 5)
      - "Liberty Within the Catholic Church" April 28, 1966 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican Council and the Jews" April, 1966 (Box 5)
      - Speech accepting Thomas Jefferson Award of the Unitarian Universalist District of Metropolitan New York April 1966 (Box 5)
      - "Liberty Within the Catholic Church" September, 1966 (Box 5)
      - "God, Theology and Love" September, 1966 (Box 5)
      - "Vatican II: Underworld of Superstition" September, 1966 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1968
      [5-13]
      - "Pope Paul, Institutional Man" January 9, 1967 (Box 5)
      - "The Man Who Murdered Verwoerd; Letter from Cape Town" March, 1967 (Box 5)
      - "Censorship and Apartheid" February 22, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Speech on censorship April 21, 1968 (Box 5)
      - "Public Money and Church Schools: Two Supreme Court Decisions" November, 1968 (Box 5)
    - 1971-1973
      [5-14]
      - Letter to editor regarding apartheid and South Africa February 14, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Comments on Supreme Court decision on tax support for parochial schools September 1971 (Box 5)
      - "The Principle of Separation" November, 1971 (Box 5)
      - "Courageous Profiles" March, 1972 (Box 5)
      - "Is Abortion Murder" May 1972 (Box 5)
      - "A Humanist Critique of Catholicism" July, 1972 (Box 5)
      - "The Church/State Battlegrounds" September, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding population control 1972 (Box 5)
      - "Darwin vs Adam and Eve in California" March, 1973 (Box 5)
      - "A Glorious Victory" May 1973 (Box 5)
        (Supreme Court decision on abortion)
      - "Parochiaid, Abortion, and School Prayer" July, 1973 (Box 5)
      - Letter to editor regarding Catholic stand on mixed religious marriages July, 1973 (Box 5)
      - Eulogy for Ed Lukas September 19, 1973 (Box 5)
    - 1974
      [5-15]
      - Comments on Sir Francis Galton's "Statistical Inquiry into the Efficiency of Prayer" [1872) January, 1974 (Box 5)
      - "Our Battle with Clerical Power" February 5, 1974 (Box 5)
      - "Christianity and Sex: An Indictment of Orthodox Theology" March, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Comments on Robert Ingersoll's "The Foundations of Faith" and "What is Religion" [1899) May 1974 (Box 5)
      - "The Vatican and Roman Jews" June, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Comments on Tom Paine's The Age of Reason [1794), July, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous writings (Box 5)
      [5-16]
    - Miscellaneous speeches (Box 5)
      [5-17]
  - Book Reviews 1928-1968
    [5-18]
    - Scott Nearing Whither China; Thomas Millard, China--Where It is Today and Why, May, 1928 (Box 5)
    - Harry F. Ward Our Economic Morality and the Ethic of Jesus, July 10, 1929 (Box 5)
    - Cleveland Rodgers The Roosevelt Program, October 21, 1933 (Box 5)
    - J.T. Salter Boss Rule--Portrait on City Politics, July 3, 1935 (Box 5)
    - Daniel W. Hoan City Government: The Record of The Milwaukee Experiment, June 10, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Charles A. Beard An Economic Interpretation of the Constitution, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Allan P. Farrell Whither American Education?, February, 1949 (Box 5)
    - George D. Smith The Teaching of the Catholic Church, April, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Joseph M. Dawson Separate Church and State Now and Alvin W. Johnson and Frank H. Yost, Separation of Church and State in the United States, September 17, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Annette Baker Fox Freedom and Welfare in The Caribbean; A Colonial Dilemma, October 1, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Stanley Walker Journey Toward the Sunlight, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Harvey S. Perloff Puerto Rico's Economic Future, January 1, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Anson Phelps Stokes Church and State in the United States, September, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Earl Parker Transformation: The Story of Modern Puerto Rico, January, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Virgil Kelly The Truth About Catholics; James M. O'Neill, Catholics in Controversy; and Archbishop Roberts, S.J., Black Popes, March, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Norman Thomas A Socialist's Faith, September, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Charles B. Kinney Church and State: The Struggle for Separation in New Hampshire, 1630-1900, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Harold C. Gardiner, S.J. Catholic Viewpoint on Censorship, December, 1958 (Box 5)
    - James MacGregor Burns, John Kennedy: A Political Profile, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Edward J. Richter and Berton Dulce Religion and the Presidency, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Harvey Cox A Baptist Intellectual's View of Catholicism, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Robert Bendiner Obstacle Course on Capitol Hill, October, 1964 (Box 5)
    - James E. Curry Churches and Zoning: Public Regulations of the Religions Use of Land, June 1965 (Box 5)
    - Xavier Rynne Vatican Council II, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Journal Articles
    - From Church and State: A Monthly Review, January 1955-August, 1962 (Box 5)
      (published by Protestants and other Americans United for Separation of Church and State)
    - From The Humanist, 1958-1965 (Box 5)
      (published by the American Humanist Association)
  - Books and Pamphlets
    - Shake Hands with 200,000 Clothing Workers, circa 1920 (Box 6)
    - An Outline of the British Labor Movement, 1923 (Box 6)
    - Labor in Southern Cotton Mills, 1927, 2 copies (Box 6)
    - What's the Matter with New York (with N. Thomas), 1932 (Box 6)
    - New York and the Seabury Investigation (edited by John Dewey), 1933 (Box 6)
    - Publications of City Affairs Committee (New York) circa 1933-1937 (Box 6)
    - How to Run a Union Meeting, 1937, 2 copies (Box 6)
      (Workers' Education Pamphlet Series no. 2)
    - The Fusion Hand Book, 1937, 3 copies (Box 6)
    - Investigating City Government in the La Guardia Administration, 1937 (Box 6)
    - The Adolescents' Court Problem and Probation and Psychiatric Care for Adolescent Offenders, 1941 (Box 6)
    - Democracy and Empire in the Caribbean, 1947 (Box 6)
    - American Freedom and Catholic Power, 1949 (Box 6)
    - My Catholic Critics, 1952, 4 copies (Box 6)
    - Democracy and Catholic Power, 1952 (Box 6)
    - The Irish and Catholic Power, 1954 (Box 6)
    - The Right to Read, 1955 (Box 6)
    - God and Man in Washington, 1960 (Box 6)
    - The Future of Catholic Power, 1961, 2 copies (Box 6)
    - Freedom and Catholic Power in Spain and Portugal, 1962 (Box 6)
    - The American Answer to Catholic Power, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Religion and the Schools, 1963 (Box 6)
    - Paul Blanshard on Vatican II, 1966 (Box 6)
    - Personal and Controversial (autobiography), 1973 (Box 6)
      (In MHC printed collection)
    - Some of My Best Friends are Christians, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Background Files for Books/Post-Publication Materials
    The largest subseries in the Writings and Related Materials series consists of Background Files and Post Publication papers accumulated on each of Blanshard's books. This eighteen feet of files has been arranged by book title and consists of assorted materials, including printed matter, newspaper clippings, and personal notes, compiled by Blanshard as background and research materials for his books. Also included are any additional information, for example reviews, related to each book. Where possible, the material was organized by individual chapters of each book.
    - Democracy and Empire in the Caribbean (1947)